-
Speaker 1: He is creating inflation. Despite the fact that he's talking about putting out the fire, he continues to pour gasoline on the fire. One thing he did not mention at all was the $40 trillion national debt. How do you not talk about that in the context of fighting inflation? That is what's helping to create the inflation. He said there also is a military option to lowering interest rates, getting bond yields down, that if we have to, we're gonna resort to our military. What the hell is he talking about? Buy these treasuries or we're going to bomb you?
today is the
Speaker 2: last podcast
i'm going to be
Speaker 3: recording for a while from my boat i've done the last several from
Speaker 4: the boat i've been on this summer vacation and the last few weeks of it have been spent on the boat we started in connecticut and now we are in maine and on monday my family and I will be flying back to Puerto Rico. So the next time I do
a pilot,
Speaker 4: I will be in my Puerto Rico studio. I want to start off today's podcast by focusing on the speech that was delivered today by Fed Chairman Kevin Warsh. And the speech, of course, was highly anticipated. I don't know why anybody cares what this guy says, because it's obvious what he's going to say. And it's also obvious that despite what he says, he's not going to do what he says. So what he says is meaningless.
Speaker 4: what he does is what counts and he doesn't do anything related to what he's talking about and of course he talks tough about inflation he's serious he's really going
Speaker 1: to bring the inflation rate down to two percent and that is exactly how the speech today was perceived
And
Speaker 1: everybody was saying it was very hawkish. Well, duh. I mean, what do you expect? He's not gonna not talk hawkish. That's his whole script. That's what he does. That's part of the Kevin Warsh show. You know, also, Trump does not criticize Warsh when he is hawkish the way he did of Powell. Again, that's all part of the show.
Speaker 1: It's to try to make everybody believe that the Fed is somehow independent and that the Fed might actually start hiking rates and shrink its balance sheet and fight inflation. But they're trying to create a situation where when he doesn't do that, it looks as if he's not politically motivated, that it's actually economically justified. So it doesn't really matter what he says. But the markets...
Speaker 1: In particular, precious metals, gold and silver really got hit hard today. And the dollar rallied based on the idea that, oh, my God, he's going to get serious this time. He's really going to start fighting inflation. In fact, the odds of a September rate hike, which stood at about 37 percent before he talked, rose to like 57 percent when he was done talking, even though nothing he said changed anything.
Speaker 1: because Warsh has been talking tough about fighting inflation since before he was nominated, and certainly even during the confirmation hearings. It was all how tough he's going to be on inflation. So what did he say today that was any different than what he's been saying?
But the fact
Speaker 1: of the matter is, despite all this tough talk, he's had multiple opportunities to hike rates, and he did not do it.
The balance
Speaker 1: sheet continues to expand.
Speaker 1: M2 continues to expand. It's expanding at about a 6% annualized rate since he got the job. He is creating inflation. Despite the fact that he's talking about putting out the fire, he continues to pour gasoline on the fire. So again, it doesn't matter what the guy says. Look at what he's doing. And what he's doing is creating more inflation. He is making the same choice
Speaker 1: that his predecessors made. But I think even more important than what Walsh said today, and I'm going to get into that, is what he did not say, because that speaks louder to me than what he chose to say. One thing he did not mention at all was the $40 trillion national debt.
How do you
Speaker 1: not talk about that in the context of fighting inflation? That is what's helping to create the inflation. Nor did he mention what is currently happening
with
Speaker 1: the U.S. Treasury and its Operation Twist, which, by the way, was expanded as I predicted it would already this week. Not only did they already double the buybacks from $2 billion to $4 billion, but earlier this week, the Secretary of the Treasury said that the U.S. government would use the general accounting fund to cover the cost.
Speaker 1: of the buybacks. And there's something like a trillion that the government could
Speaker 5: in theory now tap into to buy long-term treasuries. Now, this is not free money. I mean, this is money they
were going
Speaker 5: to spend anyway. And so if they spend this money buying back their debt, they're just going to have to issue new debt to fund the spending that they're not going to cut. The government's not going to cut any spending. They're not saying, hey, we're going to use this money to buy back debt instead of spending it for other purposes. No, they're going to keep on
Speaker 5: spending, so they're going to use this money twice, which means they've got to borrow. But it means that you're going to have an even bigger twist where the average maturity of the national debt is going to shorten by an even greater amount, meaning that the U.S. government will be in an even more vulnerable position if the Fed actually delivered on the rate hikes that the markets are now assigning a higher probability.
Speaker 5: actually taking place and again I think that's part of the show here to get the markets to think that the Fed might hike rates to try to get the benefit of tighter money without actually having tight money in fact while having loose money you get the markets to think that you're on the verge of tight money and that's what caused gold silver prices to fall the dollar to rise I'll get into the market reaction a little bit later in the podcast right now I want to stay focused
Speaker 5: on what was said. So I already mentioned what wasn't said, nothing about the reckless fiscal policy of the U.S. government, the runaway debt. And because Warsh
Speaker 1: is not addressing the elephant in the room,
you know, I know
Speaker 4: he's not going to do anything about inflation because you can't do anything about it unless you acknowledge what's really going on. In fact, while Warsh did accept responsibility for inflation, he mentioned in his talk
That
Speaker 4: for the last 65 months, inflation has been way above their 2% target. And he accepted responsibility on behalf of the Fed. Now, of course, he hasn't been at the Fed for most of those 65 months, but he accepted responsibility on behalf of everybody else at the institution. But
he said
Speaker 4: it was solely the Fed's fault. He said it was just the Fed. Basically, we own it. It's our fault and we've got to do something about it. But that's not true.
It
Speaker 4: takes two to tango when it comes to doing the inflation dance and the Fed's dance partner is the U.S. government. It's Congress and it's the president because it's the Congress that is authorizing and spending the money that it does not have.
Speaker 4: That is leading to the inflationary policy that the Fed is pursuing to make that spending possible, to avert a financial crisis or bond crisis, which would happen if the Fed did not accommodate these deficits. So when you let your partner in crime off the hook and then you claim that you're not going to commit the crime anymore, it's going to happen.
Speaker 4: Because it's impossible for the Fed to really fight inflation, given what the government is now doing. So one of the first things, though, that Warsh said when he started his talk was he talked about forward guidance and how it's outlived its purpose. And I don't think it ever really had a legitimate purpose. But he said that it was created in the aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis and that it's kind of overstayed its welcome.
Speaker 4: and that we don't need it anymore. But what happened was interest rates were at zero. And they were like, well, how do we ease policy? We got rates at zero. We're already doing QE. How can we cut where we're already on the floor? And the way they did that was through this forward guidance. And the forward guidance was, hey, we're at zero and we're going to stay there for a long time. And we're going to keep on printing money, right? Because they couldn't actually do much once they were at the zero bound. So they wanted to keep talking about how long they were going to stay
there.
Speaker 4: to try to get you know to ease policy when they really they didn't want to go negative right like some of the central banks went to negative actual nominal rates the fed didn't go there although i think at one point donald trump was agitating for that he was jealous he was saying hey other countries have negative rates why can't we right he thought that was a good idea that the fed should have tried that but you
know
Speaker 4: Warsh is saying, look, we don't need forward guidance anymore. And he said the markets should not look to the Fed. Investors should not make their next trade based on what they think the Fed is going to do. They should look at the data objectively, look at the economy, and then make their investments based on that, not based on what
Speaker 1: they think the Fed is going to do. But that's not going to happen because-
Speaker 1: What the Fed does is very important, because if you just made your decisions based on the actual economy, you would think, OK, well, rates are going to go way up because we're going to have inflation based on the actual numbers. But what markets are doing is they're trying to figure out, well, the Fed's not going to do the
Speaker 5: right thing. See, if I knew the Fed was going to do the right thing based on the data, well, then you could follow the data.
But if
Speaker 5: you believe the Fed is going to do the wrong thing, then what difference does the data make? If you know the Fed is going to be political, that the Fed is just going to try to keep air from coming out of a bubble, to artificially sustain a fake economy, to try to help politicians avoid having to face difficult decisions, how can you ignore what you think the Fed is going to do? Because the Fed is going to act based on political motivation.
not
Speaker 5: just based on the data. In fact, the data may be irrelevant to the Fed. As much as they like to say they're data dependent, the data they may depend on are political polls or the popularity of the current administration. So I think it's wrong for Warsh to even think that anybody could just take the Fed out of the picture. I mean, he's right to the extent that we shouldn't be making decisions based on what we think the Fed is gonna do. But unfortunately,
Speaker 5: We have to, traders have to, because what the Fed does moves markets and the Fed may have its own agenda that is different than what
the
Speaker 4: data would actually suggest. He also talked about the dual mandate and how they're going to continue to work for those that are not mutually exclusive because in the long run, you need low inflation to have high employment. But of course, there is a trade off.
Speaker 4: in that when you have a lot of unemployment and you create inflation and wages don't go up as much as prices, you're lowering wages. You're lowering the minimum wage. And to that extent, you do help employment somewhat because you're making labor cheaper by lowering wages, real wages. So in effect, you can help the unemployment problem to the extent that the unemployment problem was created
by
Speaker 4: wages being too high. And so inflation is a kind of surreptitious way of lowering wages because you're lowering the real cost of employment, which might result in more demand for workers.
But in
Speaker 4: general, I agree with the idea that in the long run, low inflation and low unemployment would go hand in hand. But the political pressure in the short run, whenever there is a rise in unemployment, is for the Fed to stimulate the economy.
And
Speaker 4: the only thing the Fed could do to stimulate the economy is create inflation. Now, in the long run, that undermines the economy. But in the short run, it can deliver a stimulus that may help the employment situation. And Warsh doesn't really acknowledge that fact. Now he also said that he has the view.
Speaker 4: that money matters, that money matters to monetary policy as if it's some kind of unorthodox, outside the box view that's out of fashion. Like money supply has nothing to do with money or monetary policy. Ironically, when it comes to inflation, it has everything to do with policy because that's what's being inflated. You can't even talk about inflation without talking about
Speaker 4: The definition of inflation is the expansion of the money supply. That's what's being inflated, money and credit. The result is that prices go up. So he's saying that he has an unorthodox view that money matters. Of course it matters. I mean, look at even Milton Friedman's quote. Inflation is always a monetary phenomenon.
Speaker 4: In other words, money is all that matters, yet somehow to a lot of people, it doesn't matter at all. But if you understand that money matters and you look at what's happening to money supply, you know, it doesn't matter what Kevin Warsh wants to say about fighting inflation. Look at the money that he is creating because he is creating inflation. Now, he also said.
Speaker 4: focused on the 2% target by saying that it is a firm, fixed target, that that's their target. It's not 2.2, 2.5, certainly not 2.9, it is two. And he specifically referenced two inflation measures, the 12-month
PCE,
Speaker 4: increase of 3.7% year over
Speaker 1: year and the six months change of 4.1%, which is double the Fed's 2% target. So again, he played lip service to the fact that our target is 2%. And despite the fact that we have missed it for 65 consecutive months, do not doubt our resolve. We are going to reduce inflation to 2%.
Speaker 1: and you better believe it. We are totally serious this time. Maybe we weren't serious before, but we're as serious as cancer. We've got all these task force that we have created. We're on the job. We mean business, and you better not doubt us. That is what impacted the markets. All this tough talk, it's like, how many times are the markets gonna get fooled by the same talk? You know, it reminded me, and I put something on X about this, of Lucy and Charlie Brown and the football, where Lucy holds that football
Speaker 1: And tells Charlie Brown, hey, I'm going to hold it. You can kick it. Don't worry.
This
Speaker 5: time I'm not going to take it away. And every time he goes to kick it, she yanks it away. And Charlie Brown, he just believes her. He just assumes, okay, I'm finally going to kick that football. Yet he never does. The same thing happens with these rate hikes. They keep saying, you know, we're going to hike. Hut, hut, hike. We're going to hike rates. And the markets get all ready for these rate hikes. And then Warsh pulls the ball.
Speaker 5: right out from under them and they're in
Speaker 1: the bother ass
so i
Speaker 1: don't put any stock into anything that war said unfortunately or fortunately depending on your perspective the
Speaker 3: markets do the fed chairman spoke at jackson hole on friday depending on which outlet you read he either reassured everybody or he warned them usa today ran the headline quote fed chair impressed by u.s economy still hopes to tame inflation the new york post covered the same speech with quote Warsh says there's work to do on inflation, sparking bets
on a
Speaker 3: rate hike next.
Speaker 3: month. One of those makes you feel better about your portfolio. The other tells you borrowing costs are about to go up. Same man, same podium, same words. That's why I use Ground News. It's an app and a website that pulls every story together in one place so you can read every headline side by side.
Speaker 3: This one speech had 247 outlets covering it. You can also see who owns each source because ownership shapes the narrative. The New York Post and Fox Business both carry the same tag. Murdoch family right there on the screen and their blind spot feed surfaces the stories one side of the media barely covers at all. I've built my whole career on looking past the headline number to the actual data. Ground News lets you do that with the news itself. So go to groundnews.com slash shift and you'll get 40% off their unlimited access podcast.
Speaker 3: vantage subscription that works whether you subscribe yourself or send it as a gift but make sure you use my link groundnews.com slash shift so you get the discount and they know i sent you if you like this podcast you're going to like their mission that's groundnews.com slash shift
Speaker 4: before i forget i want to mention that the real estate guys are doing their annual summit at sea on sand this year and the sand is the beaches of puerto rico
And
Speaker 4: they're doing the conference just before we're doing our SHIFT Sovereign Plan B conference in Panama City. So the summit at S.A.N.D. is September 13th through the 17th. There's still time to register. I know it's not that far away, but if you want to come down, there's still some slots available September 13th to the 17th.
Speaker 4: Just go to their website, Investor Summit on Sand, Real Estate Guys. If you want to go to both, if you want to go to our event, Shift Sovereign, there's still some room there. And if you want to go to both, I probably have room for a few people to fly with me on my jet from Australia.
Speaker 4: San Juan to Panama City. So a few of you might be able to come on board with me. There are commercial flights, though, that go direct from San Juan to Panama City. So you will be able to get there. And then, of course, you can go home from Panama City. If you don't want to do the real estate, guys, of course, you could simply join me in Panama City for the Plan B conference. Anyway, I want to get back to the Warsh talk and the market reaction.
Speaker 1: And again, what's more significant is...
is that he
Speaker 1: completely ignored what Treasury is doing. A lot of people
Speaker 4: were wanting to get Warsh's reaction, and there was no reaction. He acted as if it wasn't even happening. In fact, another thing that Trump said during
the week,
Speaker 4: this is not Warsh. He was doing a Fox News
Speaker 1: interview about this policy, Operation Twist.
Speaker 1: And he acknowledged that yes, this is what we're doing now, this market intervention. But he said there also is a military option to lowering interest rates, getting bond yields down. That if we have to, we're gonna resort to our military, to using that option. What the hell is he talking about? How is it a military intervention? How can the U.S. military intervene
to
Speaker 1: lower bond yields. I mean, what are we going to do? Are we going to threaten foreign countries? Are we going to try to extort them into buying our treasuries or else? Like, hey, buy these treasuries or we're going to bomb you or we're just going to withdraw our troops? We're not going to protect you anymore? I mean, I don't even know what this military option is that apparently Trump has up his
Speaker 4: sleeve because Fox didn't do any follow-up.
Speaker 4: Because that's what I would have done. The minute I heard him say, we've got this military option, I would have said, well, what? In fact, while Trump was also talking about using the military to fight a war against rising bond yields, he
Speaker 5: also escalated the trade war against Canada. Remember, on the last podcast, he was talking about how we were close to this great deal with Canada. Well, shortly after that, the whole deal blew up.
Speaker 5: And so Trump imposed 50% tariffs on a lot of Canadian goods, and the Canadians have already retaliated with tariffs of 15%, 25%, and 50% on U.S. goods. Now, it was a mistake for Trump to hit Americans with these tariffs again. The way Trump frames it, he's hitting Canada.
Speaker 5: But he's not hitting Canada. Canada doesn't pay our tariffs, we pay our tariffs. It was the Canadian government that hit the Canadians when they retaliated. That's how stupid a trade war is. Because America is punishing its citizens,
Canada
Speaker 5: retaliates by saying, well, if you're going to punish your citizens, well, we're going to punish our own citizens. How do you like that? Right. I mean, what kind of crazy war is this where the object is to kill yourself? Right. But that's what's going on. But it's all politics because Carney wants to act like he's doing something like, oh, I got to be tough. If Trump is going to impose tariffs, well, we're going to impose tariffs, even though Canada would be better off if they just ignored it.
what
Speaker 5: Trump was doing and left their tariffs where they were or even lowered the tariffs. Trump keeps talking about how Canada has been ripping us off and taking advantage of us for years. How are they even doing that? We don't even have a real trade deficit with Canada. I mean, some years it's a deficit, some years it's a surplus. Every year it's a deficit in goods. That goes without saying. I mean, we've got a deficit in goods with
Speaker 1: everybody,
but we
Speaker 1: have a surplus in
Speaker 4: services.
Speaker 4: we sell a lot of services that the Canadians buy. And so net-net, you know, the trade is kind of balanced. So
Speaker 1: how are they ripping us off? I mean, even if we were running consistent deficits, it wouldn't mean they
Speaker 5: were ripping us off. But if that's your definition of a rip-off, then it's not even happening the ridiculous way that Trump keeps score. But he's done this. In fact, one of the things now he's doing to try to win this war is he's already renamed Lake Ontario
Speaker 5: Lake America, like that's really going to matter. It's like being on a playground saying your mama, right? We're changing the name. First of all, it's been
Speaker 1: Lake Ontario for like 400 years. I'm not even sure, I don't think there was a Canada back then. There certainly wasn't in America. We've only been around for 250. So,
Speaker 1: Ontario,
Speaker 5: the origin of Ontario is in Canada. Maybe the province got named after the lake or it's named after the same thing that they named the lake after. It's not called Lake Ontario just because a lot of it happens to be in Ontario. But Trump decided that we're gonna call it Lake America, just like we have the Gulf of America. Not like changing the name of the Gulf of Mexico
Speaker 5: to the Gulf of America did nothing to reduce our trade deficits. It didn't improve anything, nor will changing the name of Lake Ontario. In fact, we got trade deficit numbers that came out for July. And the deficit exploded in goods, 18%, 118.8 billion. Imports soared by 3.7%.
Speaker 5: And exports tanked by 2.9 percent. Obviously, the tariffs are not working. This was the worst trade deficit since March of 2025. And the reason the March of 2025 deficit was so big was because everybody was front running the tariffs. So you had some big deficits in early 2025, unusually big.
Speaker 5: because importers were trying to bring stuff in before they were going to be subject to the tariffs. So it's not even an apples to apples comparison.
Then in
Speaker 5: order to get a trade deficit as big as the one we just got in July, you got to go back to early 2022, just after we opened the economy from the COVID lockdowns. And so there you had all this pent up demand. You had all these goods that were sitting on the docks. We couldn't import them.
And
Speaker 5: so when all of a sudden we reopened the economy, the trade deficits really shut up because all these goods that we weren't importing during the lockdown, we suddenly brought them in. But those are outliers. That's the only time you can get a trade deficit as bad as the one we have now is when you have a real exogenous event that we don't really have now. And so it just shows you that the trade relationships are deteriorating despite everything that Trump has done. And in fact,
Speaker 5: If you want to look at Canada's GDP growth versus ours, we announced our GDP earlier in the week, I think it was Wednesday, annualized Q2 GDP 1.5% in the US. Canada reported their Q2 GDP growth today, annualized, at 3.3%. So Canada has got economic growth double the economic growth in the United States. So clearly,
By that
Speaker 5: measure, Canada is winning the trade war, right, because they've got a stronger economy. In fact, in order to deal with soaring beef prices, Trump announced that he was going to be, I think, suspending some quotas and lowering tariffs on imported beef so that beef prices would fall. And he was very happy to announce that he's going to be lowering these tariffs, right?
But
Speaker 5: wait a minute, you're the reason the tariffs are there. You impose tariffs, and now you're claiming credit for taking them away? And he's taking the tariffs away specifically because he says the result will be lower prices. Well, that's an admission that the tariffs raise prices. Because after all, if removing tariffs lowers prices,
Speaker 5: It's only because imposing them raises prices, because otherwise it wouldn't be true. It can't be that just taking away tariffs makes prices go down, but they don't go up at all when you impose the tariffs. Otherwise, there's no reason for them to drop. So his own...
Speaker 5: Policy is a repudiation of his policy, yet he continues to come out with these asinized statements about how strong the economy is, how great the economy is, how the tariffs are working. They're clearly not working. The trade deficits are getting bigger. They're not getting smaller. And prices are going up. They're not coming down. He's not living up to any of his promises, so he decides to rename lakes. Okay.
Speaker 5: this is not about marketing. America doesn't have a branding problem. We don't need to name more bodies of water after America. In fact, he's talking about renaming one of the oceans. I don't know if he's joking or not, but he said, you know, we don't have an ocean. We got a lake, we got a Gulf, we need an ocean. So we need the American ocean. So I guess it's either the Atlantic or Pacific are next, right, and now they're gonna be called the American ocean. But all this is form over substance. It's to kind of pretend
that
Speaker 5: he's actually doing something about problems that he's not only not solving, that he's making worse. And it's the same thing going on at the Fed. It's all talk. Warsh knows that he has no choice but to choose inflation. But he's not going to say that. And he knows that since he really doesn't have a stick,
He
Speaker 5: has to speak very loudly, which is what he is doing. He is talking tough as if he's really going to do something about this high inflation. And the markets, the markets are taking him seriously. So let's get to the markets, although I expect the markets to reverse a lot of what happened today. Now, the stock market was
Speaker 4: down across the board today, but not very much. The Dow only dropped about 10 points and was actually up on the week by 0.4%.
Speaker 4: S&P dropped a quarter of a percent today, but it was also a percent on the week. The Nasdaq down about a half a percent today, but up 1.4 percent on the week. So tech still getting some money flowing into it. That was probably helped by the NVIDIA earnings, which beat estimates. The small caps were actually down, down on the week and on the day, down 1.4 percent today.
Speaker 4: Down 1.2% on the week. So the Russell 2000 was up up until today and it lost all of its gains and then some. But the big action was in precious metals. Gold dropped 3.2% today, over $140 an ounce, and down 4.75% on the week. We closed around $4,454.40 on the price of gold. Silver got beat up.
Speaker 4: even more, especially if you look at the intraday reversal in the price of silver. But silver was down 4.4% on the day. Silver closed at 66 and a quarter. But intraday, silver almost hit $71.
Speaker 4: today. So that was a new high for this move ever since we had the big correction. In fact, gold almost got to $4,700, got to $4,680. So it too had a big reversal, but not nearly as big as the silver reversal. Gold and silver stocks also, as you would expect, got beat up. The GDX was down 3.9% on the day, 4.4% on the week.
Speaker 4: GDXJ down 4.4% on the day and about the same amount on the week. So pretty much all the losses coming today. Intra week, though, interesting. Newmont Mining, the world's biggest gold mining company and the only gold mining company in the S&P 500, hit a new all-time record high today. All-time high. Even though gold itself
Speaker 1: would have to rally another 20% to get back to its record high that it hit, I think it was January or February of this year.
Speaker 1: Newmont has already hit a new
Speaker 4: high, and that is a very strong leading indicator that investors are waking up to the reality of rising gold prices and starting to realize that gold is not going to collapse and starting to revise their earnings forecasts and build those higher forecasts into a present value and bidding up the stock.
Speaker 1: Some gold miners really leading and making new highs before the metal itself, I think, is a positive sign that we are going to be making new highs in both gold and silver. And by the time we do, of course, the mining stocks, I think we're going
Speaker 4: to be considerably higher than they are right now. Now, Bitcoin was down about one and a half percent, although it hasn't really ended the week. Bitcoin keeps trading over the weekend.
Speaker 4: But based on where it was a week ago, Friday to Friday, Bitcoin is down one and a half percent. It was down three percent today. Right now, as I'm recording this, Bitcoin is trading at about seventy seven thousand four hundred. It got above eighty one thousand five hundred overnight. So also a big reversal.
Speaker 4: In Bitcoin itself, strategy was down 7.3% today. Had a huge gain yesterday. Not really sure where that came from. Probably a lot of short covering. There was, again, this was another big week, or last week rather, where a lot of strategy stock was sold. The Bitcoin yield collapsed now on strategy. It's now negative on the year.
Speaker 4: So Bitcoin strategy has destroyed common shareholder value during the year. Common shareholders own fewer Bitcoin now per share than they did when the year began. So it's a huge destruction of shareholder value that nobody is acknowledging. But a lot of this is about trying to get the stretch price back to 100%.
Speaker 4: Now, it's closer to 100, but it's still not there. It closed at 97.33, down 0.7% on the day, but up 1% on the week. But the yield is 12.3%. So he still has to dilute common shareholders even more in order to try to get stretch up to 100. And he's going to have to keep diluting them in order to keep it at 100. So it is a losing
Speaker 1: game. I don't know where that rally came from in strategy other than short covering. I still say there's a death spiral.
Speaker 1: Even if it's going to live a little longer, thanks to this rally in Bitcoin. Remember, Bitcoin rallied from about 60,000 up to over 80,000, in large part because of the operation twist announced by the Treasury. Bitcoin kind of
Speaker 4: followed gold's lead. But I think this is going to be short-lived. I think you're going to see a lot of selling in
Speaker 1: Bitcoin, and that is bad news for strategy and stretch. Oil prices actually softened a bit on the week. We close around 8.
Speaker 1: and a half from 87 last week. But I think the bigger story is in the bond market and the dollar. Dollar index shot up to 99.66. Pretty much all the gains happening today following Warsh's tough talk. But look at that dollar yen. The yen dropped. Now it's back above 160. So the yen could be under a lot of pressure on Sunday night, meaning more intervention, more treasuries being sold, which means more treasuries at the US government.
is
Speaker 1: going to end up buying and the yield on the 10-year Treasury rose on the week. I think we settled at 4.72. That was up a bit from where we settled last week. The 30-year actually slipped ever so slightly, closing at 5.21. But the yields were lower intraday and then reversed and the bonds closed on the lows of the day.
so
Speaker 1: it's not looking good for next week and again all of this is going to complicate warsha's commitment to bringing down inflation because the more upward pressure there is on long-term interest rates the harder it's going to be for the fed to actually do that if in fact it was its intention to ever do that because now it needs to mop up the liquidity
Speaker 1: that the Treasury is adding to the market. It's going to have to counteract the goals of Treasury to try to reverse what they're doing, and it's not going to happen. Talk
to
Speaker 3: any manufacturer in this country right now, and you'll hear the same thing. The pressure is coming from every direction. Rising energy costs, a tight labor market, supply chains that are still fragile, and cyber threats that get worse every quarter. This isn't one problem you can solve and move on. Rockwell Automation just put out their 11th annual state of smart manufacturing.
Speaker 3: report. They surveyed over 1,500 decision makers across 17 countries, and what they found is exactly what you'd expect if you've been paying attention. 90% of manufacturers say digital transformation isn't optional anymore. It's the price of staying competitive. But here's where it gets interesting. Only 43% of the data these companies collect is actually being used. The rest just sits there. That's enormous value left on the table, and nearly half of them, 46%, were hit by a cyber incident in just the past
Speaker 3: year. As factories get more connected, that risk lands directly on the balance sheet. If you run a manufacturing business or you invest in one, this report is worth your time. Download it for free at rok.auto/sosm. That's rok.auto/sosm.
Speaker 4: Now there are a couple of other economic data points that I wanted to discuss today. One was personal income and spending numbers, which came out
Speaker 4: A little bit in line, personal income was up 0.4. The expectation was up 0.2, but personal spending was up 0.2 versus the 0.3 from the prior month. But what was significant was the PCE, which rose more than expected. Month over month, the personal consumption expenditure index rose 0.2. Expectations were for a rise of 0.1. It fell 0.1 the previous month, and year over year,
The
Speaker 4: rise was 3.7, which matched the prior month. It was supposed to decline slightly to 3.6. Now, Warsh actually mentioned this number today in his talk as a reason that the Fed has to remain vigilant about getting inflation to 2% because it remains so much higher than 2%. Another thing that Warsh did discuss, and I forgot to mention this, because he spent the first part of his talk all on AI and how great the economy was
Speaker 4: and attributed it to artificial intelligence and the productivity boom that's coming. In fact, he referred to AI as a fourth factor of production. There are three factors of production. If you know basic economics, you have land, labor, and capital. And he is saying that maybe AI is a fourth factor. Now, I would consider it capital.
But
Speaker 4: you could create an entire new factor of production and say, well, it's not really labor or capital and just say it's a fourth factor of production that obviously competes with the others, particularly labor. And he talked a lot about the job losses that may flow from AI. In fact, a lot more people, Bill Gates, I saw interviews with him and a lot of other people are talking about
Speaker 4: these substantial job losses that may come. And one of the reasons that they say it's different than job losses that maybe we got from the Industrial Revolution
or something
Speaker 4: like that is the sheer magnitude of how many jobs can be eliminated and how quickly they can be eliminated. So the transition from losing your job to a computer or to a robot and getting some other job
Speaker 4: maybe a lot longer than what we've experienced in the past. And so this is going to be a huge political challenge for government.
But I
Speaker 4: don't really want to get into that during this podcast. But Warsh talked about it as if everything is great in America, the economy is booming, but it's not because we got one piece of economic data
Speaker 5: that came out today that strongly shows otherwise. And that was the Chicago PMI that was supposed to rise from 57 and a half in July Bye-bye.
to
Speaker 5: 59 in August. Instead, it collapsed all the way down to 47.1. This is the lowest reading on the Chicago PMI since December of 2025, so the low reading of the year. But what's more significant is the magnitude of the miss. This is the biggest downside surprise in the Chicago PMI since February 2015.
Speaker 5: So that's more than 11 years ago we had to miss this bad. So this strongly suggests that the economy is not nearly as robust as everybody likes to claim. Yes, the stock markets are doing well because some companies got a lot of profits that are in on the AI trade. But Houston has a problem here that nobody wants to acknowledge. And I want to round out today's podcast, though, by talking about.
Speaker 5: a problem in one industry that's particularly relevant to where I'm doing today's podcast. And that's what's happening in the U.S. in the boat industry.
Speaker 4: And it is an excellent example of how monetary policy creates booms and busts, because the boat industry is going through a bust right now. You may not know that if you're not in the market for a boat or you don't own a boat that you're trying to sell, but
Speaker 5: But this is a huge bust that's only going to get worse for boating. And people are thinking, hey, Peter, you know, why did you buy a boat? Why didn't you wait if you're so smart about predicting this stuff? Well, the particular boat that I bought, there really are no used ones for sale because they weren't making these electric solar power boats. And the people that have them don't want to sell them. In fact, one of the big problems in the boating industry is the cost of the diesel because the boats run on diesel.
And
Speaker 5: diesel prices have gone up a lot more than gasoline prices because a lot of the oil that makes its way through the Straits of Hormuz, that's the oil that ends up becoming marine diesel. And so those prices are really up, but it doesn't affect me so much because I'm electric, I got solar power, and so I'm very fuel efficient. So if anything, there might be more demand for an electric solar powered boat.
now
Speaker 5: that diesel prices are so high and again if you're curious about the kind of boat that i have it is a sun reef 60 power eco this is the smallest one they make but if i had gotten one size bigger i couldn't be at this marina i mean i have a lot more mobility with this size boat i mean it's about as big as i can get into most places without having to anchor far out so there are a lot of things that i could do on the 60 and with a 35 foot beam i'm not wanting for space it seems very very spacious.
Speaker 5: interested in a boat like this check out their website at sun reef and you can see my boat they make bigger ones this model they make all the way up to 100 and you can get them in an eco version or you can get a regular power and of course they make them with a sail which is the most efficient because you're not using any power at all when you're under sail and so there may be some demand for sailboats right now
Speaker 5: But overall, the boat industry is in a perfect storm. And that's what I want to explain right now. I think it's a perfect backdrop to talk about what's happening in boats because this same thing is going to be happening in housing too, right? Because in many cases, a boat is a house, right? You could live on a boat. It's like a floating house. And in fact, a lot of these boats were purchased.
As
Speaker 5: floating homes, vacation homes, they were purchased during COVID. So let me go back in time a little bit to the COVID pandemic. So COVID hits, and
no one can
Speaker 5: go anywhere. All the cruises are canceled. The airlines aren't flying. People aren't going to work. People are stuck at home,
and they
Speaker 5: can't go out in public. So what was something that they could do? They could go on their own boat.
They
Speaker 5: can go out to sea, you're on a boat, right? Nobody else is around. You don't have to wear a mask on your own boat, right? But it seemed like a perfect place to spend the lockdown, right? To me, have my own boat. And what also was going on at that time, the Fed had interest rates at zero. A lot of people who buy boats borrow their money to buy the boats. They took out a boat loan. Well, those loans were also very low cost when interest rates were at zero. Remember, long-term treasury yields...
Speaker 5: were under one percent. So it was very easy to borrow a bunch of money. So during the lockdowns, gas was cheap. Interest rates were cheap. So a lot of people, when they were penciling the numbers, "Hey, how much is it gonna cost me to go out and buy a boat?" You know, they had an unrealistic expectation of what the operating costs would be of that boat. Now, the other operating costs, of course, are a dock,
and
Speaker 4: then insurance, and then spare parts.
Speaker 4: because you know boats break down especially if you're buying an older boat a used boat which a lot of people did um because we weren't even making the shipyards
Speaker 1: were shut down there was actually a shortage of new production so there was a lot of demand for the used boats because those are the ones that were there so prices
Speaker 4: went way up because a lot of people wanted to buy boats and they had the money because interest rates were really cheap and so this created a lot of demand but the costs are also the insurance
And
Speaker 4: if you want to put your boat on a dock, which most people do, the marina is going to require that you have insurance.
And if
Speaker 4: you borrow money to
buy a
Speaker 4: boat, the lender is going to require insurance because the boat's the collateral for the loan. If the boat sinks, right, where
are you
Speaker 4: going to get the money? So they want to make sure that you've got it insured.
So
Speaker 1: there are a lot of these costs that seemed worth it.
And of
Speaker 1: course, all of this extra demand fueled by cheap money and the COVID lockdowns and all that and cheap gas
is,
Speaker 4: A lot of people went out and bought a certain types of boats. They bought a lot of boats that were like vacation homes, trawlers, not necessarily fishing boats, but boats that were like 40, 50 to 60 feet, big enough to have three or four cabins, but really living space where you can spend the vacation, kind of like a floating RV, right? People were buying these things. Now, there were also people that were buying a lot of these catamarans and
In
Speaker 4: the BVI, you had companies like the Mooring, they were selling them as investments because you'd buy a boat and you'd stick it there in their inventory and they would rent it out, do these leases. People would be renting your boat constantly, but you would buy it. You'd buy a boat and you'd stick it there in their inventory and they would rent it out, do these leases. People would be renting your boat constantly, but you would buy it.
And
Speaker 4: they would manage it, and then you'd get to use it. But there was a lot of demand, too, there because it seemed like a good idea. I could use the boat sometimes. I could get some cash flow by having it chartered out. And so there was a big glut. Well, what's going on now? Well, several things have happened. First of all, there is no more COVID lockdown. So people are back to traveling. If you want to go on a cruise, you can go on a carnival cruise. You can get on an airplane. You can fly down to wherever you
Speaker 1: want to go. So you have a lot more options.
Speaker 1: So a boat doesn't seem quite as appealing as it did during COVID. Interest rates have gone way up on boat loans in particular, right, because the Fed's not monetizing those. So now if somebody wants to buy
Speaker 4: a boat, it's a lot more expensive because of the higher interest rates. But it's not just the higher interest rates that have gone up.
Speaker 4: It's the insurance rates have gone way up, because insurance companies took a lot of losses with a lot of natural disasters. So it's a lot more expensive to insure the boat, assuming
Speaker 1: that you can even afford to buy the boat. But of course, people that already own boats, they got to pay the insurance. Their insurance wasn't locked in.
And a
Speaker 1: lot of these boat loans, these could be variable rate loans. The loans
could go
Speaker 1: up. Then you've also got the cost of fuel.
fuel
Speaker 1: costs are up dramatically. So
Speaker 4: assuming you have a boat, a
lot of
Speaker 4: people can't even afford to use it because it's too expensive to motor it. So it's just sitting there on the dock burning a hole in their pocket. You know, there's an old joke about boats, right? What are the two best days of a boat owner's life? The day he buys it and the day he sells it. Because what you find out when you own a boat is you don't use it nearly as much as you think.
Speaker 4: It's a lot cheaper just to charter a boat
for the
Speaker 4: few times you actually use it. So you've got this boat that's sitting in a marina. And the slip fees have gone up a lot too, right? They've increased. Inflation has driven that up. So you've got this boat that's sitting on a dock that's now more expensive.
Speaker 4: And now your insurance has gone up. And in fact, if you bought an older boat, if your boat, like the hull is maybe 40, 45 years old, a lot of insurance companies won't even write the policy anymore. Now you're really stuck because you're in a situation where you're required to have insurance, but you can't even buy it. But assuming you get your insurance, your insurance is going up.
The
Speaker 4: slip fees are going up, the interest on the boat loan has gone up, and you can't even afford to use it because the gas is so expensive or the diesel. So what are all these people doing? They're trying to sell their boats. What's going on with these catamaran companies in the BVI? They're trying to unload. These boats that were
Speaker 1: bought in 2021, 2022, a lot of them now up for sale, and they're trying to replace them with newer models. There's a huge inventory of these charter boats that nobody really wants to buy anymore.
Speaker 1: So, boat prices have collapsed. Boat prices are down like 40, 50%. Use boat prices, certain boats, not all boats. Now, yes, you would expect boat prices to go down over time, right? Boats are a depreciating asset, but they generally depreciate more slowly than a car. But we've seen a rapid
Speaker 4: depreciation in the boats that a lot of people were buying as a result of COVID. There's a glut
of
Speaker 1: these things on the market.
that
Speaker 1: have now gone down. And in fact, look at West Marine. They are the biggest boat supply store in the country. They had about 200 locations, obviously concentrated in states where there's boating. They filed for bankruptcy on May 11th of this year. Bankruptcy. They've already announced that 93
of
Speaker 1: their 200
Speaker 4: some odd stores are being closed across 28 states. So
Speaker 1: 45% of West Marine stores are getting shuttered. Now this company has been in business since 1968. They changed the name to West Marine in 1977. They opened their first store in California in 1975. And so now they had 200 stores until they went bankrupt. But look at the history of this company. Oh, and by the way, what are the reasons
Speaker 1: that they're going bankrupt is because so many people who own boats aren't using their boats. See, if you can't afford to use your boat, you don't need the supplies, right? Because you're not using the boat. So you don't need the stuff that you
Speaker 5: would normally buy. If your boat's just sitting there on the dock, you don't need as much stuff as when you're out there using it.
Speaker 5: That's the problem. And of course, fewer people are buying new boats because when you buy a new boat, all of a sudden there's a rush of things that you need and you buy to equip your new boat that maybe the boat didn't have when you bought it. So because there's not as many people buying boats and because the people who own boats can't afford to use their boats, West Marine went bankrupt. But part of the reason for the bankruptcy was the leverage. It got levered up because.
Speaker 5: the cheap money. So not only did the government create the boom in boating that bust by the ridiculous COVID lockdown policy and the 0% interest rates, but they also fueled the leverage buyouts that levered up West Marine, because West Marine didn't have much debt. And so it probably could have survived a downturn in the boating market, but it couldn't survive
the
Speaker 5: the downturn in the bond market and the increase in interest rates. So what happened,
Speaker 4: so the company went public. So I said it started in 1968. They went public in 1993. Now, I didn't know all this stuff. I had to research it a little bit before I did the podcast, right? But, you know, I mean, I was familiar with the West Marine. I knew they went bankrupt, but I didn't know all the nitty gritty here. But so they went public in 1993.
with
Speaker 4: about a 90 to a 95 million dollar valuation. So it was a very small IPO. In 2017, the company
was
Speaker 1: bought out in a private transaction for $338 million.
Speaker 4: So not a bad return. The people that bought the stock, they tripled their money, although it took 20 some odd years to do that.
Speaker 1: I don't know if they paid any dividends along the way, but it got bought out at a $338 million valuation.
Speaker 1: Then in 2021, during the COVID lockdowns, when interest rates were zero and at the peak of the boating bubble, when everybody was buying boats, it got bought again. It got sold in a leveraged buyout for $825 million. So in just a four-year time period, you more than doubled
Speaker 1: the valuation of the company, but what made it possible to pay $825 million was the company took on a lot of debt
and it
Speaker 1: couldn't service that debt in the downturn and it's now bankrupt. And so all of this, right, this whole boom and bust, which should have been obvious. I mean, they levered up at the exact peak as if that COVID boat demand was going to continue and as if interest rates were always going to be low.
Speaker 1: But they're not. You know, when you're looking at a bubble, oftentimes people extrapolate as if the good times are never going to end. And they base their decisions on these bubble circumstances. Well, it's not just in the boating industry. This is a microcosm. This is one particular example.
Speaker 1: this boom and bust and how you can directly attribute it, lay it at the feet of the Fed and the artificially low interest rates that not only created the boat bubble, but enabled investors to lever up on cheap money in order
Speaker 4: to overpay for West Marine. And West Marine is not the only bankruptcy. There is others. This is just the biggest one. Other companies in boating have already gone bankrupt. And there's probably
Speaker 1: going to be more bankruptcies.
Speaker 1: Now, I guess the good news is if you want to buy a boat, right, you're going to get your opportunity. And in fact, I think they're going to get even cheaper, particularly the types of boats are going to get cheaper. So it is a buyer's market and it's going to get better, I think, because the situation is going to get worse within the industry. Now, of course, if you buy a boat now, you know, it's probably going to keep falling. So I would still lowball.
You
Speaker 1: know, it's taken people a year, more, you know, you list a boat unless you are very aggressive right now. And again, there
Speaker 5: are certain types of boats that people will still buy because there's not as many of them, right? So if you want a particular boat and there aren't a glut of those, then yes, you know, the seller doesn't have to fire sail the boat to get rid of it.
Speaker 5: But there are a lot of boats that are very interchangeable, that
are very
Speaker 5: similar, especially like these mass-produced power cats. You know, they're about,
you know, 40 to
Speaker 5: 50 foot four cabin hulls. I mean, there's a glut of these and these trawlers
Speaker 1: that are out there. There are a bunch of
Speaker 4: those boats that are on the market and
more are
Speaker 4: gonna be coming on the market. I think the banks are gonna end up with a lot of these boats 'cause a lot of the boat owners are gonna end up just giving the boats to the bank. Now, I don't know to what degree
Speaker 4: There could be recourse where the banks could go after the boat owners for whatever's left over. But if you bought a boat 2021, 2022, and you paid, let's say, $300,000 for that boat and you borrowed $200,000 against it. So you put up 100 grand and you borrowed, you took out a boat loan and that boat now is worth 125, maybe 150,000 tops and you owe 200,000. I
Speaker 1: mean, you can't even sell it.
Speaker 1: Because if you sell it, you end up writing a check to the bank. See, normally you think, oh, I'm going to sell something, I'm going to get paid, right? I'm going to sell my boat and I'm going to get the money. No. If you are underwater on a boat loan, when you sell your boat, you have to write a check to the bank. Who the hell wants to do that? So there may be a lot of people right now that are still trying to get out of jail by selling their boat.
Speaker 1: for maybe more than the boat loan. But when they realize they can't get that, when the only way they can sell this boat and get out from under the insurance, the slip fees and all that is to take a loss, well, then they'll just send the keys to the bank
Speaker 4: and say, hey, it's your problem. And now the bank's got to figure out where to put it. Because, hey, I'm not going to pay the slip anymore. That's your boat. Now you got to pay the slip fee. And if you don't want to do that, you got to haul the boat out of the
water.
and
Speaker 4: put it somewhere you got to store it and you still got to insure it
it can
Speaker 4: still get damaged and the boat just sits there and it's going to depreciate further so the banks the lenders the boat lenders are going to have a bigger problem with all these repossessed boats and so they're going to be highly motivated right if you think they're motivated to sell a repossessed car the
are
Speaker 4: nothing like the carrying costs on a repossessed boat. I think the prices are going to get better. So if you want to experience the best day in a boat owner's life, it's going to be a lot cheaper. I'm not sure
Speaker 1: how great the relief is going to be for the seller. It may not be the best day of his life when he's selling the boat and then writing another check to get the albatross
out
Speaker 1: from around his neck but all the criticism aside of boating you know i love it i really love being out on the water i enjoy it and so yeah it's an expensive hobby but for me i think it's worth it and again yeah i would only buy a boat if you're prepared to spend a lot of money operating it i mean because again
Speaker 1: buying the boat isn't the big deal it's maintaining the boat it's the operating costs of keeping the boat that's why a lot of people end up selling it they don't count on that they can afford to buy it they just can't afford to keep it especially since they don't use it a lot but now again it's the perfect storm because it is so expensive to use these boats anyway that's it for today's podcast again
Speaker 5: if you like the podcast make sure and give it a thumbs up if you're watching on youtube click and subscribe to my youtube channel and also go to follow me on other social media on facebook on instagram on tick tock and in particular on x i now have over 1.7
Speaker 5: million x followers i should hit two million before the end of the year with your help of course and the important thing is not just following me on x but every time i post repost what i posted so more people get to see it and hopefully they'll repost it because i am getting out the truth i am putting out the truth and most of the media is putting out regurgitated government propaganda it's important that people understand
Not
Speaker 5: only what's happening, but why it's happening. So they don't get suckered into governments trying to blame the crisis on capitalism and use it as a means to usurp even more power and exploit the crisis that they caused by using it as a catalyst to make government bigger. I want people to realize that it's big government that is the reason
Speaker 5: that we're having these problems. That's what Trump should be focusing on. Instead of coming up for a new name for Lake Ontario, cut government spending. That's something he can actually do. He talks about the trade deficits, which are getting worse. He doesn't actually have direct control over those, but he does with the veto pen and the bully pulpit over the budget deficits. That's something the government can control. We need less government. We don't need to rename our lakes,
Speaker 5: We need to substantially drain the swamps, cut government spending, and not just the waste, fraud, and abuse that they couldn't even cut with Doge, but we need to cut the meat on the bone, not just the fat. So I'm spreading that news on social media. So again, follow me
Speaker 4: on X and help me spread that word. And I will be back again doing my regular podcasts from my Puerto Rico studio sometime next week. So bye for now.
you